Finding Aid for the Allen Sigel Collection of Scores, 1946-1998
State University of New York at Buffalo. Music Library
Allen Sigel Collection of Scores, 1946-1998
Mus. Arc. 32
Sigel, Allen
10 boxes (102 folders)
State University of New York at Buffalo. Music Library
The Allen Sigel Collection of Scores, 1946-1998 contains approximately 27 compositions by Allen Sigel. Many of them are present in multiple versions. There are also ten works by other composers in arrangements by Sigel and three of his didactic works for clarinet.
Administrative Information
Terms of Access
Materials can be examined by qualified researchers in the Music Library during hours of operation during which Music Librarians are present. In order to insure access, researchers are advised to contact the Music Library in advance of visits.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Allen Sigel, April 2004.
Accruals and Additions
No further accruals are expected to this collection.
Biographical Note
Allen Sigel was born 9 February 1925 in Chicago, Illinois. He spent his youth in Ottumwa, Iowa and began his studies in clarinet at the age of eleven. He earned his bachelor's degree at the University of Iowa where he studied clarinet with Hymie Voxman and earned a master's degree in 1947 at the Eastman School of Music in Rochester, New York.
Allen Sigel served as principal clarinetist with the Buffalo Philharmonic Orchestra 1948-1960 (with the exception of the 1950-1951 season) and served on the music faculty at the University at Buffalo beginning in 1953. In 1960 he joined the faculty full time and served until 1992. He also taught in other positions in Iowa, Kentucky, and California. He wrote three books on clarinet instruction, including The Twentieth Century Clarinetist. In 1986 Sigel traveled to China to lecture and perform. He served as music director for the Jewish Center of Buffalo and was an instructor in the Elder Hostel program where he taught a course, Composers of the golden age of American musical theatre.
Allen Sigel died in Williamsville, New York 15 March 2013.
Scope and Content Note
The collection contains 102 folders holding approximately 27 compositions by Allen Sigel, ten works by other composers in arrangements by Sigel, and three of his didactic works for clarinet. Many of the compositions exist in multiple versions and some were reworked altogether and renamed. For example, the melody to his Patriots all, which he submitted as an entry in a competition to select a new national anthem for the United States, is the same as that of his U.B., our University, a candidate to become the alma mater for the University at Buffalo.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged in three series:
I. Compositions
II. Arrangements of works by other composers
III. Clarinet methods and etudes
Container List
- Compositions, 1946-1998, I.; Folder 1-85
  Arranged alphabetically by first element of the uniform title. Movements within works are filed in order as presented in the work.
  - Sigel, Allen Americana suite Americana suite for woodwind quintet, 1995, 3 manuscript scores (76 p.; 28 cm)and 5 manuscript parts; Arranged for flute, piccolo; oboe, English horn; clarinet, French horn, and bassoon. Includes 3 holograph (photocopy) scores with minor differences and a complete set of 5 holograph (photocopy) parts. (Box 01, Folder 001)
  - Sigel, Allen Bartokiana Bartokiana for violin, B? clarinet, and piano, 1996, 4 manuscript scores (9 pages; 28 cm) and 2 manuscript parts; Accompanied with a letter addressed to Allen Sigel from Nancy Braithwaite expressing interest in obtaining a copy of Bartokiana. Contains 1 holograph (pencil) score and 1 ink score, 1 incomplete holograph (ink) score, 1 spiral-bound photocopied score, holograph (ink) violin part, and photocopy of clarinet part. (Box 01, Folder 002)
  - Sigel, Allen Casual developments Casual developments for clarinet and string quartet, 1996, 1 manuscript score (15 p.) and 8 manuscript parts; Dedicated to Ken Grant. Includes 1 holograph (photocopy) score of the 3rd movement, 4 photocopied parts of the 1st movement, and 4 manuscript (ink) parts for the 3rd movement. A tacet is indicated for the 2nd movement for all instruments. (Box 01, Folder 003)
    Contents: Cloning--Fantasia (tacet)--At Odds.
  - Sigel, Allen Dorothy Parker On men Dorothy Parker on men: poems of Dorothy Parker set to music, 1994, 1 manuscript score (9 p.) and 2 manuscript parts; Holograph (ink) For soprano, oboe, bassoon, and piano. Accompanied by photocopy of typescript letter form Sigel to Andrew D. Weinberger seeking permission to use Parker's poems. Includes 1 holograph (ink) score with markings of 2 poems, and 2 manuscript (ink) parts of 2 poems. (Box 01, Folder 004)
    Contents: Chant for dark hours--Coda.
  - Sigel, Allen Eppes klezmer Eppes klezmer for B?clarinet and piano, 1998, 3 manuscript scores (14 pages; 28 cm) and 1 manuscript part; Related to Shtetl echoes, composed in 1995. Includes 1 holograph (ink) score with corrections, 1 photocopy with additional markings for the piano part, 1 pencil score, and 1 manuscript (ink)part for clarinet with markings and another photocopy without markings. (Box 01, Folder 005)
  - Sigel, Allen Flapper era dances Flapper era dances nonet, undated, 3 manuscript scores (14 p.)and 9 manuscript parts; Consists of 1 manuscript (pencil and ink) score with corrections, 2 holograph (photocopy) scores (1 spiral-bound), 9 manuscript (pencil) parts and an additional set of photocopied parts with further markings. (Box 02, Folder 006)
    Contents: Tango-maxixe.
  - Sigel, Allen Flapper era dances Flapper era dances for saxophone quartet, 1994, 2 manuscript scores (27p.), manuscript sketches, and 4 manuscript parts; Arranged for soprano, alto, tenor, and baritone saxophone. Accompanied with a letter containing information about the premiere of flapper era dances, which took place on Monday, October 10 1994. Also contains tempo and articulation instructions for each part. Contains 1 holograph (pencil) score of all 4 movements with corrections and 1 spiral-bound holograph (photocopy) score, 4 photocopied parts and a separate folder containing manuscript (pencil) sketches of all 4 movements. (Box 02, Folder 007)
    Contents: Tango--Hesitation waltz--Fox-Trot variations--Charleston.
  - Sigel, Allen Flapper era dances Flapper era dances for clarinet and string quartet, undated, 1 manuscript score (10, 15, 15 p.) and 5 manuscript parts; Arranged for B?clarinet, violin I and 2, viola, and violoncello. Charleston is marked movement 3 on manuscript parts and movement 4 on the score. Contains 1 manuscript (pencil) score of all 3 movements, 1 photocopy of the 3rd movement with additional markings, and 5 manuscript (pencil) parts. (Box 02, Folder 008)
    Contents: Tango--Fox-Trot variations--Charleston.
  - Sigel, Allen Four nations suite Four nations suite for piano, four hands, 1997, 3 manuscript scores (12 p.) and manuscript sketches; Includes 1 spiral-bound holograph (pencil) score with list of corrections, 2 spiral-bound holograph (photocopy) scores with additional markings, and manuscript sketches: variation of the 1st movement, sketch of movements 3 and 4. (Box 03, Folder 009)
    Contents: France-homage to Francis Poulenc--Spain-homage to Manuel De Falla--Israel-homage to Ernest Block--Hungary-homage to Béla Bartók.
  - Sigel, Allen Four nations suite Four nations suite for piano and saxophone quartet, undated, 3 manuscript scores and 4 manuscript parts; Arranged for piano, soprano, alto, tenor, and baritone saxophone. Consists of 1 manuscript (ink) score of all 4 movements, 1 manuscript (pencil) score of all 4 movements, 1 photocopy of movement 4 with markings for clarinet and violin, and 4 manuscript parts of all 4 movements. (Box 03, Folder 010)
  - Sigel, Allen From then 'till now From then 'till now: suite for oboe or soprano saxophone and strings, 1995, 1 manuscript score (35 p.); Accompanied with an analysis of all 4 movements. The baroque concerto is based on Johann Sebastian Bach's keyboard concerto in C minor BWV 981--an arrangement of Benedetto Marcello's op. 1 no.2. Includes 1 spiral bound manuscript (ink) score of all 4 movements. (Box 03, Folder 011)
    Contents: Baroque concerto--Classical rondo--Romantic serenade--Twentieth century scherzo.
  - Sigel, Allen Garland for Gershwin Garland for Gershwin: for C clarinet and piano, undated, 3 manuscript scores (11 p.); Includes 1 holograph (ink) score with corrections, and 2 holographs (photocopy) with additional markings. (Box 03, Folder 012)
    Contents: Overture.
  - Sigel, Allen Homage to Gershwin Homage to Gershwin: for B? clarinet and piano, undated, 3 manuscript scores and manuscript sketches (10 p.); Includes 1 holograph (ink) score of all 3 movements, 2 photocopies of the 3rd movement of the holograph score with additional markings, and 10 pages of manuscript sketches for the 3rd and 1st movements. (Box 03, Folder 013)
    Contents: Overture--Blues--Swing finale.
  - Sigel, Allen Homage to Gershwin Homage to Gershwin: for B? clarinet and piano, undated, 3 manuscript parts; Accompanied by a cover sheet that dedicates the piece to Tom Ridenour. Contains 1 holograph (ink) part for B? clarinet for the 1st and 3rd movements, 1 photocopy of the 2nd movement, and 1 manuscript (pencil) cadenza that proceeds the 2nd movement. (Box 03, Folder 014)
  - Sigel, Allen Homage to Gershwin Homage to Gershwin: for B? clarinet and piano, undated, 1 manuscript score (13 p.); Includes 13 pages of manuscript (pencil) sketches for the 3rd movement. (Box 03, Folder 015)
  - Sigel, Allen Homage to Gershwin Homage to Gershwin: piano solo, undated, 3 manuscript scores (5 p.); Includes 1 holograph (pencil) score, 1 manuscript (ink) score with corrections, and 1 holograph (photocopy) with further markings. (Box 03, Folder 016)
  - Sigel, Allen Homage to Gershwin Homage to Gershwin: for saxophone quartet, 1993, 4 manuscript scores; Arranged for soprano, alto, tenor, and baritone saxophone. Accompanied with a description of the piece. Dedicated to the Amherst Saxophone Quartet. Includes 1 holograph (ink) score of all 3 movements, 2 holograph (photocopy) scores of the 3rd movement with differences, and 10 pages of manuscript sketches. (Box 03, Folder 017)
  - Sigel, Allen Homage to Gershwin Homage to Gershwin: for saxophone quartet, 1993, 5 manuscript parts; Arranged for soprano, alto, tenor, and baritone saxophone. Includes 4 holograph (photocopy) parts of all 3 movements, and 1 holograph (photocopy) of the 1st movement part for alto saxophone. (Box 03, Folder 018)
  - Sigel, Allen Homage to Gershwin Homage to Gershwin: for woodwind quintet, undated, 2 manuscript scores (10 p.) and 5 manuscript parts; Arranged for flute, oboe, B? clarinet, French horn, and bassoon. Contains 1 manuscript (pencil) score, 1 incomplete manuscript (pencil) score, and 5 manuscript (pencil) parts. (Box 04, Folder 019)
  - Sigel, Allen Homage to Prokofiev Homage to Prokofiev for B? clarinet and piano, 1959, 4 scores (23 p.) and 4 parts; Includes 2 holograph (photocopy), 1 trimmed and taped to create performance copy for pianist. The performance copy contains additional markings including an optional cut. 1 manuscript copy (ink) with photocopy containing additional manuscript replacement pages. 1 manuscript (ink) part for B? clarinet and 3 photocopies with different markings. (Box 04, Folder 020)
  - Sigel, Allen In Gershwin's garden In Gershwin's garden: trio for clarinet, violoncello, and piano, 1993, 3 manuscript scores (24 p.) and 2 manuscript parts; Includes 1 holograph (pencil) score of both movements, 2 holograph (photocopy) scores, and 2 manuscript (ink) parts. (Box 04, Folder 021)
    Contents: Overture, cadenza--Swing.
  - Sigel, Allen Jerusalem 3000 Jerusalem 3000, 1996, 2 manuscript scores (32 p.) and 4 manuscript parts; Accompanied with program notes. Includes Hatikva score. Includes 1 spiral bound photocopy of holograph score with additional markings; 1 photocopy of the holograph score (not bound) with other markings; ink manuscript parts for violin I and II, viola, and violoncello, heavily marked with bowings. Also included are additional unmarked photocopies of the violin II, viola, and violoncello. (Box 04, Folder 022)
    Contents: Ancestors--King David--Exodus--Hava nagilah--Jerusalem city of gold--Hatikva.
  - Sigel, Allen Jerusalem 3000. Ancestors Patriarchs, 1996, 1 manuscript score; Pencil draft of Ancestors, movement of Jerusalem 3000. (Box 04, Folder 023)
  - Sigel, Allen Jerusalem 3000. King David Bar kochba, 1996, 1 manuscript score; Pencil draft of King David, movement of Jerusalem 3000. (Box 04, Folder 024)
  - Sigel, Allen Jerusalem 3000 Exodus, 1996, 1 manuscript score; Pencil draft of Exodus. (Box 04, Folder 025)
    Contents: Ancestors--King David--Exodus--Hava nagilah--Jerusalem city of gold--Hatikva
  - Sigel, Allen Jerusalem 3000 Hava nagilah, 1996, 1 manuscript score; Pencil draft of Hava nagilah. (Box 04, Folder 026)
  - Sigel, Allen Jerusalem 3000 Jerusalem city of gold, 1996, 1 manuscript score; Pencil draft of Jerusalem city of gold. (Box 04, Folder 027)
  - Sigel, Allen Moods, clarinet, piano Two moods for B? clarinet and piano, undated, 1 manuscript score (10 p.); Holograph (Pencil) Accompanied by 7 photocopied pages from The Twentieth Century Clarinetist: Advanced Studies in Contemporary Music for the Clarinet by Allen Sigel. (Box 04, Folder 028)
    Contents: Prologue--Jubilation.
  - Sigel, Allen Moods, clarinet, piano Two moods for B? clarinet and piano, undated, 2 manuscript scores (10 p. each) and 2 manuscript parts (3 p. each); For both score and clarinet part there are holographs (Ink master on blueprint paper) and ozalid reproductions of the holographs. (Box 04, Folder 029)
  - Sigel, Allen Moods, clarinet, piano Two moods for B? clarinet and pianoforte: Prologue and jubilation, undated, 1 manuscript part (3 p.); Subtitle added to first movement: Homage to Ernest Bloch. Holograph (Ink) with additional photocopy of pages 2-3 with some changes. (Box 05, Folder 030)
  - Sigel, Allen Moods, clarinet, piano Two moods for B? clarinet and pianoforte, undated, 3 manuscript scores (9 p. each); Ink holograph score with two photocopies each with additional and different markings. Scores may have been intended for use as piano parts. (Box 05, Folder 031)
  - Sigel, Allen Nocturne Nocturne, 1997, 1 manuscript score (3 p.); Dedicated to Emily. 1 holograph (ink) score with markings. (Box 05, Folder 032)
  - Sigel, Allen Nostalgic suite Nostalgic suite: for solo clarinet and wind ensemble, 1995, 1 manuscript score (77 p.); Dedicated to clarinetist John Fullam and the University at Buffalo wind ensemble. 1 holograph (photocopy) score marked "original complete." Accompanied by photocopy of last movement (p. 49-77) with additional markings. (Box 05, Folder 033)
    Contents: Broadway overture--Blues--Swing variations.
  - Sigel, Allen Nostalgic suite. Selections [Nostalgic suite]. Broadway overture; Blues: for solo clarinet and wind ensemble, 1995, 1 manuscript score; 1 holograph: Broadway overture is a photocopy with some additional markings; Blues is an ink holograph. (Box 05, Folder 034)
  - Sigel, Allen Nostalgic suite. Selections [Nostalgic suite]. Blues; Swing variations: for solo clarinet and wind ensemble, 1995, 1 score (55 p.); Computer-notated score with small number of additional markings. (Box 05, Folder 035)
  - Sigel, Allen Nostalgic suite. Broadway overture [Nostalgic suite]. Broadway overture: "corrected copy" for solo clarinet and wind ensemble, 1995, 1 score (27 p.); Computer-notated score marked "corrected copy" with additional markings and accompanied by printout of the ending measures 258-266 in a differently formatted version. (Box 05, Folder 036)
  - Sigel, Allen Nostalgic suite. Broadway overture [Nostalgic suite]. Broadway overture: for solo clarinet and wind ensemble, 1995, 1 score (26 p.); Computer-notated score with additional markings. (Box 05, Folder 037)
  - Sigel, Allen Nostalgic suite. Broadway overture Nostalgic suite. Broadway overture: for solo clarinet and wind ensemble, 1995, 1 score (25 p.); Computer-notated score with additional markings and changes. (Box 05, Folder 038)
  - Sigel, Allen Nostalgic suite. Broadway overture [Nostalgic suite]. Broadway overture: "partially corrected copy," [1995] for solo clarinet and wind ensemble, 1995, 1 score (26 p.); Computer-notated score with additional markings. (Box 05, Folder 039)
  - Sigel, Allen Nostalgic suite. Blues [Nostalgic suite]. Blues: "partially corrected" [1995] for solo clarinet and wind ensemble, 1995, 1 score (17 p.); Computer-notated score with additional markings. (Box 05, Folder 040)
  - Sigel, Allen Nostalgic suite. Blues [Nostalgic suite]. Blues: for solo clarinet and wind ensemble, 1995, 1 score (14 p.); Computer-notated score with additional markings. (Box 05, Folder 041)
  - Sigel, Allen Nostalgic suite. Swing variations [Nostalgic suite]. Swing variations: "partially corrected" [1995] for solo clarinet and wind ensemble, 1995, 1 score (41 p.); Computer-generated score with additional markings. (Box 05, Folder 042)
  - Sigel, Allen Nostalgic suite Nostalgic suite: clarinet part, 1995, 1 manuscript part; 1 ink manuscript of all 3 movements. (Box 05, Folder 043)
  - Sigel, Allen Nostalgic suite [Nostalgic suite]. Parts, 1995, 31 parts; Computer-notated parts with additional performance markings. Missing oboe 1 part for Swing variations. (Box 05, Folder 044)
  - Sigel, Allen Nostalgic suite [Nostalgic suite]. solo clarinet part, 1995, 8 folders; 8 computer-generated scores for solo clarinet part. Folders 1-4 contain 4 versions of the 1st movement with corrections. Folders 5 and 6 contain 2 versions of the 2nd movement with corrections, and folders 7 and 8 consist of 2 versions of the 3rd movement with corrections. (Box 05, Folder 045)
  - Sigel, Allen Nostalgic suite [Nostalgic suite]. Recording [1995], 1995, 1 cassette tape; Cassette recording. 1 cassette tape with complete recording on B-side. (Box 05, Folder 046)
  - Sigel, Allen Patriots all Patriots all: (song version), June 1992, 1 manuscript score (2 p.); Holograph (Ink) First line of text: Patriots all, united are we in the cause of sweet liberty. Words by Allen Sigel. Accompanied by 6 photocopies of the text and a notice from Anthem America about the contest for a new national anthem. 1 holograph (ink) score with markings. (Box 06, Folder 047)
  - Sigel, Allen Patriots all Patriots all: [song version], June 1992, 1 manuscript score (2 p.); Holograph (Pencil) First line of text: Patriots all united are we in the quest of sweet liberty. Words by Allen Sigel. 1 holograph (pencil) score with markings. (Box 06, Folder 048)
  - Sigel, Allen Patriots all Patriots all: [song version], June 1992, 1 sketchbook; Holograph (Ink and pencil) First line of text: Patriots all united are we in the quest of true liberty. Words by Allen Sigel. Spiral-bound book also contains sketches for the song and an arrangement of Duke Ellington's Sophisticated lady and Paris blues. (Box 06, Folder 049)
  - Sigel, Allen Patriots all; arr. Patriots all: [choral version], 1992, 1 manuscript score (2 p.); Holograph (Ink) First line of text: Patriots all, united are we, in the cause of sweet liberty. Words by Allen Sigel. Setting for soprano, alto, tenor, bass voices with piano accompaniment provided for rehearsal only. (Box 06, Folder 050)
  - Sigel, Allen Patriots all; arr. Patriots all: [choral version], 1992, 1 manuscript score (1 p.); Holograph (Pencil) First line of text: Patriots all united are we in the cause of sweet liberty. Words by Allen Sigel. Setting for unaccompanied soprano, alto, tenor, and bass voices. (Box 06, Folder 051)
  - Sigel, Allen Patriots all Patriots all: [piano part], 1992, 1 manuscript part (2 p.); Holograph (Ink) 1 holograph (ink) score with markings. (Box 06, Folder 052)
  - Sigel, Allen Patriots all; arr. Patriots all: [choral version with second verse], 1992, 1 manuscript score (2 p.); Reproduction of holograph. Twenty-eight copies of setting for soprano, alto, tenor, bass voices with piano accompaniment provided for rehearsal with 2nd verse of text written in red between the staves of the piano part. First line of text: Patriots all, united are we, in the cause of sweet liberty. Words by Allen Sigel. (Box 06, Folder 053)
  - Sigel, Allen Patriots all; arr. Patriots all: [choral version], 1992, 1 score (4 p.); Photocopy of printed score with photocopy of 1 page of holograph score attached. First line of text: Patriots all, united are we, in the cause of sweet liberty. Words by Allen Sigel: this version includes 3 verses. Setting for soprano, alto, tenor, bass voices with piano accompaniment for rehearsal. (Box 06, Folder 054)
  - Sigel, Allen Patriots all Patriots free: [song version], June 1992, 1 manuscript score (2 p.); Photocopy of holograph with manuscript additions. First line of text: Let us unite as patriots free in the search for true liberty. Words by Allen Sigel. Variant version of music and text of Sigel's Patriots all. (Box 06, Folder 055)
  - Sigel, Allen Poe potpurri [Poe potpurri [sic] for narrator, trumpet, and saxophone quartet], undated, 1 manuscript score (55 p.); Accompanied with 4 photocopied leaves of Poe texts marked in preparation for use. Holograph (Ink) score. The score is in two groups. The pages in the first group run p. 1-23 in one direction and then p. 24-39 return in the opposite direction on the verses, so the verse of p. 23 is p.24, the verse of p. 22 is p. 25 and so on. The second group is paged in normal fashion as p. 40-55 (Box 06, Folder 056)
    Contents: The haunted palace--A dream within a dream--The masque of the red death.
  - Sigel, Allen Poe potpurri, voice, trumpet, saxophones (4) A Poe potpurri [sic] for narrator, trumpet, and saxophone quartet, undated, 1 manuscript score (55 p.); Holograph (Photocopy) with additional markings, including notes on A dream to score saxophone parts for string quintet. (Box 06, Folder 057)
  - Sigel, Allen Poe potpurri, trumpet, saxophones (4). Masque of the red death Masque of the red death: 1st draft, undated, 2 manuscript scores (12, [5] p.); Holograph (Pencil) The 5 page score is marked "extra." For piccolo, trumpet (at opening), and saxophone quartet with text for narrator written on same pages. Accompanied by 3 photocopied leaves of the text of the Poe story. (Box 06, Folder 058)
  - Sigel, Allen Poe potpurri, clarinets (4) Poe 2 Cl. 4tet, undated, 1 sketchbook; Holograph (Pencil) Title from card attached to cover. Also includes sketches for Sigel's Dorothy Parker On men. (Box 06, Folder 059)
    Contents: Alone--The haunted palace--A dream within a dream.
  - Sigel, Allen Poe potpurri, clarinets (4) Alone; The haunted palace; A dream within a dream: for clarinet quartet, 1993, 4 manuscript parts; Holograph (Ink) The haunted palace and A dream within a dream movements are versions of the same movements in Sigel's Poe potpurri for narrator, trumpet, and saxophone quartet. Each part contains 3 fascicles with separate title pages corresponding to the 3 movements. (Box 06, Folder 060)
  - Sigel, Allen Poe potpurri, saxophone, strings. Selections. A dream within a dream; Moving, 1995, 1 manuscript score (p. 35-60); An oboe can be substituted for the soprano saxophone part. Holograph: Dream within a dream is an ink holograph; Moving is a photocopy of a holograph with additional changes. The movements are marked III and IV respectively. (Box 07, Folder 061)